





# Postdoc Researcher

# BIO

I am a Uruguayan biologist (PhD) doing research in macroecology and biodiversity informatics. Currently, I am a postdoc researcher at the Czech University of Life Sciences (MOBI Lab), focused on the study of spatial and temporal patterns of biodiversity. I am also the founder of Biodiversidata (Uruguayan Consortium of Biodiversity Data), a member of the JULANA NGO, the admin for NaturalistaUY (the iNaturalist site for Uruguay), and a NatGeoExplorer.

# **EDUCATION**

2013 – 2017	Ph.D., Life Sciences University of Lincoln, United Kingdom Evolution and Ecology Research Group, School of Life Sciences. Dissertation: Biodiversity in- formatics and macroecological patterns of biodiversity: Uruguay as a model region. Advisor: Daniel Pincheira-Donoso
2013 – 2015	M.Sc., Biological Sciences (Genetics)  Department of Biodiversity and Genetics, Clemente Estable Biological Research Institute. Dissertation: Contributions of molecular ecology to the study of mammals in Uruguay. Advisors: Susana González and Mariana Cosse
2006 – 2012	B.Sc. (Hons), Biological Sciences  Universidad de la República, Uruguay  Department of Biodiversity and Genetics, Clemente Estable Biological Research Institute.  Project: Development of molecular tools for the taxonomic identification of different carnivore species. Advisor: Mariana Cosse

## PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

PROFESSIONAL EXPE	RIENGE
04/2021 - present	Postdoc Czech University of Life Sciences (Czech Republic) Range dynamics of Neotropical carnivores in the MOBI Lab, Department of Spatial Sciences.
01/2021 - 04/2021	Intern UN Environmental Programme - World Conservation Monitoring Centre (Cambridge, UK) Knowledge Management internship in the Conserving Land and Seascapes Team
08/2018 - 12/2020 part time	<b>Demonstrator</b> Demonstrating for courses of Zoology, Paleontology, and Biological Anthropology at the School of Life Sciences
01/2017 - 07/2017 part time	<b>Project Manager</b> Co-coordination of the project 'Conservation in private protected areas of Uruguay'
11/2016 - 03/2017	Research Assistant Universidad de la República (Montevideo, Uruguay) Bioinformatics and genomics at the Department of Animal Genetics, School of Veterinary
10/2016 - 11/2016	<b>Field Assistant</b> Sampling plots of vascular plants for the project 'Rural Futures'
11/2015 - 10/2016 part time	<b>Technician</b> Livestock pedigree data management  Rural Association of Uruguay (Montevideo, Uruguay)
11/2015 - 10/2016 part time	Research Assistant Universidad de la República (Montevideo, Uruguay) Bioinformatics and comparative genomics of Salmonella at the Institute of Hygiene, School of Medicine
01/2012 - 12/2015	Research Assistant Clemente Estable Biological Research Institute (Montevideo, Uruguay) Research and teaching at the Department of Biodiversity and Genetics
05/2012 - 04/2014 part time	<b>Teaching Assistant</b> Universidad de la República (Montevideo, Uruguay) Organization of outreach ativities at the Extension Unit, School of Science

### **PEER-REVIEWED ARTICLES**

- 1. Pincheira-Donoso D., Harvey L.P., <u>Grattarola F.</u>, Winter M., Jara M., Cotter S.C., Tregenza T. & Hodgson D.J. (2021) The multiple origins of sexual size dimorphism in global amphibians. *Global Ecology and Biogeography*, 30(2): 443-458. [link]
- 2. <u>Grattarola F.</u>, Martínez-Lanfranco, J.A., ... & Pincheira-Donoso D. (2020) Multiple forms of hotspots of tetrapod biodiversity and the challenges of open-access data scarcity. *Scientific Reports*, 10(1): 1-15. [link]
- 3. <u>Grattarola F., Mai, P., ... & Pincheira-Donoso D. (2020) Biodiversidata: A novel dataset for the vascular plant species diversity in Uruguay. *Biodiversity Data Journal*, 8: e56850. [link]</u>
- 4. <u>Grattarola F.</u> & Rodríguez-Tricot L. (2020) Mammals of Paso Centurión, an area with relicts of Atlantic Forest in Uruguay. *Neotropical Biology and Conservation*, 15(3): 267–283. [link]
- 5. D'Alessandro B., Pérez Escanda V., Balestrazzi V., <u>Grattarola F.</u>, ... & Betancor L. (2020) Comparative genomics of Salmonella enterica serovar Enteritidis ST-11 isolated in Uruguay reveals lineages associated with particular epidemiological traits. *Scientific Reports*, 10: 3638. [link]
- 6. <u>Grattarola F.</u>, Botto, G., ... & Pincheira-Donoso D. (2019) Biodiversidata: an open-access biodiversity database for Uruguay. *Biodiversity Data Journal*, 7: e36226. [link]
- 7. <u>Grattarola F.</u> & Pincheira-Donoso D. (2019) Data-sharing in Uruguay, the vision of collectors and data users. **Boletín de la Sociedad Zoológica del Uruguay**, 28(1): 1-14. [link]
- 8. Bergós L., <u>Grattarola F.</u>, Barreneche J.M., Herández D., & González S. (2018) Fogones de Fauna: an experience of participatory monitoring of wildlife in rural Uruguay. *Society & Animals*, 26(2), 171-185. [link]
- 9. Chouhy M., Santos C., Gaucher L., <u>Grattarola F.</u>, ... & Perazza, G. (2017) At the frontiers of knowledge: the quest for an integral training course on society-nature. *Integralidad Sobre Ruedas*, 4(1): 62–77. [link]
- 10. Cosse M., <u>Grattarola F.</u> & Mannise N. (2017) A novel real-time TaqMan<sup>™</sup>PCR assay for simultaneous detection of Neotropical fox species using noninvasive samples based on cytochrome C oxidase subunit II. *Mammal Research*, 62(4): 405-411. [link]
- 11. <u>Grattarola F.</u>, Hernández D., ... & Rodríguez-Tricot R. (2016) First record of jaguarundi (Puma yagouaroundi) (Mammalia: Carnivora: Felidae) in Uruguay, with comments about participatory monitoring. *Boletín de la Sociedad Zoológica del Uruguay*, 25(1): 85-91. [link]
- 12. <u>Grattarola F.</u>, Cosse M. & González S. (2015) A novel primer set for mammal species identification from feces samples. *Conservation Genetic Resources*, 7: 57–59. [link]

## **GRANTS, FUNDING**

2022	Capacity Enhancement Support Programme Global Biodiversity Information Facility (GBIF) £14,000   Project 'Extending knowledge on biodiversity data quality and publication in the Spanish-speaking community' CESP2021-007 [link]
2021 - 2022	<b>Citizen Science for Species Discovery Grant</b> \$25,000   Project 'Naturalista UY - The iNaturalist community for Uruguay' (Uruguay)
2019	<b>College of Science Grant for Postgraduate Students</b> £750   Attend the conference 'Biodiversity Next' (Leiden, The Netherlands)
2019	<b>Travel Grant for Postgraduate Students</b> £500   Attend the course 'Advancing in statistical modelling for evolutionary biologists and ecologists using R' (Glasgow, Scotland)
2018	Mobility Fund for Postgraduate Research Students  \$\text{Santander - University of Lincoln}\$  \$2500   Deliver the 'First meeting of the members of Biodiversidata' (Montevideo, Uruguay)
2018	Travel Grant for Early Career European Researchers & Scientists \$2,500 \ Attend the '11th RDA Plenary Meeting' (Berlin, Germany)\$
2017 - 2020	Ph.D. International Fellowship National Agency for Research and Innovation (ANII) £49,000   Postgraduate Fellowship POS_EXT_2016_1_136663 (Lincoln, United Kingdom)
2017	<b>Travel Grant for Postgraduate Students</b> Centro Brasileiro-Argentino de Biotecnologia (CBAB/CABBIO) £1,800   Attend the Course 'Bioinformatics' Tools for RNA-Sequence Data Analysis' at Labo-

ratório Nacional de Computação Científica (Petrópolis, RJ, Brasil)

2015		<b>nts</b> Association of Universities of the Montevideo Group (AUGM) de Biodados, Universidade Federal de Minas Gerais
2013	Internship Grant for Postgraduate Students Program for the Development of Basic Sciences (PEDECIBA) £1,500   Internship stay at Bioinformatics at the Department of Biochemistry and Molecular Biology, University of Mississippi (Starkville, United States)	
2013 - 2015	Posgraduate National Fellowship £8,500   Postgraduate Fellowship POS_NA	National Agency for Research and Innovation (ANII) C_2012_1_8976 (Montevideo, Uruguay)
2012	Travel Grant £1,500   Attend the 'VIII Genetic Worksho (Chillán, Chile)	Latin American Network for Conservation Genetics (REGENEC) op for Conservation: new tools and new concepts'
2012	Mobility Grant £2,000   A semester at Universidade Estad	Association of Universities of the Montevideo Group (AUGM) dual de Jaboticabal (UNESP) (Jaboticabal, SP, Brazil)
2011 - 2012	Posgraduate National Fellowship	National Agency for Research and Innovation (ANII)

# STUDENTS

Enzo Cavalli, BSc (Honours) in Biological Sciences, School of Science, Universidad de la República. Project: 'Effects of livestock on the mammal community of Paso Centurión, Cerro Largo'. Advisor, finished in 2019.

Rodrigo Montiel, BSc (Honours) in Biological Sciences, School of Science, Universidad de la República. Project: 'Biodiversity informatics and community science in Uruguay'. Advisor, ongoing.

# **LECTURING**

2017 – 2019 two editions	<b>Modern Mammals</b> School of Science, Universidad de la República (Uruguay) Lecture in the graduate course of Palaeontology, for 15-20 students. Invited by Dr. Richard Fariña [slides]	• .
2018	<b>Management and analysis of camera trap records using R</b> Ministry of Environment (Uruguay)  Course for NGOs, researchers and government people. Taught together with Juan M. Barreneche and Gabriel Perazza [syllabus]	• •
2016 – 2017 two editions	Introduction to Python  Universidad de la República, Uruguay Lecture at posgraduate course 'Introduction to command line and programming for bioinformatic analysis', for 25-30 students in Biological Sciences. Invited by Dr. Andrís Iriarte [syllabus]	infor-
2013 – 2017 four editions	Relationships between Society and Nature  Graduate course for 10-20 students of Anthropology, Biology, Geography and Social Sciences. Taught together with Carlos Santos, Javier Taks, Magdalena Chouhy, Andrea Garay, Lucía Bergós and Gabriel Perazza [link to S&N Group]	ences.
2014	<b>Environmental education and community involvement</b> Lecture at posgraduate course 'Conservation biology' for 15-20 students in Biological Sciences. Invited by Dr. Susana González.	• •
2014	Introduction to Biology Discussion group for the course Introduction to Biology School or 15-20 undergraduate students of Biological Sciences. Taught together with Dr. Juan Cristina.	• .

#### SERVICE FOR JOURNALS

CITATION METRICS

Google Scholar (04/2022)

75 citations, h-index = 5

**ACADEMIC MEMBERSHIPS** 

**Biodiversity Data Journal**. Global Ecology and Biogeography

Journal of Biogeography

2021 - International Biogeography Society. 2020 - GBIF Biodiversity Open Data Ambassador.

2019 - Organization for Women in Science for the Developing World (OWSD).

2018 - British Ecological Society (BES).

2018 - Research Data Alliance (RDA) - SHARC Interest Group.

2013 - Interdisciplinary Group on Society-Nature Relationships (RETEMA). 2012 - Latin American Network for Conservation Genetics (REGENEC).

2010 - Zoological Society of Uruguay (SZU).

## **TALKS**

2021 As a naturalist in my country, where are there more opportunities to fill in information gaps? Online Grattarola F.\* & Barreneche J.M. / LatinR Conference [code repo]

2021 Roundtable: Activism through digital media

Montevideo, Uruguay

Grattarola F.\* / 4th Conference on Digital Citizenship [video]

2021 The value of open education policies to promote environmental education Online <u>Grattarola F.</u>\* / CILAC Latin American Open Science Forum [video]

2020 Hotspots of biodiversity and the challenges of open-data scarcity

Online

Grattarola F.\* / Seminar of the Department of Spatial Sciences, Czech University of Life Sciences Prague

2019 Biodiversity hotspots in Uruguay: real or fabricated? Grattarola F.\* & D. Pincheira-Donoso / British Ecological Society Annual Meeting [slides]

Belfast, Northern Ireland

2019 Biodiversidata: a collaborative initiative towards open data availability in Uruguay

Leiden. The Netherlands

Grattarola F.\* & D. Pincheira-Donoso / Biodiversity Next Conference [abstract]

2019 Biodiversity data in Uruguay: a long way to go

Leiden The Netherlands

Invited Grattarola F.\* / Biodiversity Informatics 101 Workshop at Biodiversity Next Conference

2019 Biodiversity hotspots in Uruguay

Lincoln, United Kingdom

Grattarola F.\* & D. Pincheira-Donoso / School of Life Sciences Postgraduate Symposium, University of Lincoln

2019 iNaturalist as a tool to enhance the conservation of biodiversity in Uruguay Grattarola F.\* / Rufford Conference Uruguay [video]

Maldonado, Uruguay (online)

2017 Landscape genetics of the crab-eating fox Cerdocyon thous (Carnivora: Canidae) Montevideo, Uruguay Grattarola F.\*, Bartesaghi L., Hernández D., Soutullo A., Mannise N., González S. & Cosse M. / IV Uruguayan Zoology Congress

2016 Humans and fauna in Paso Centurión (Cerro Largo) from an interdisciplinary perspective La Paloma, Uruguay Chouhy M.\*, Garay A., Bergós L., Gaucher L., Perazza G., Grattarola F. & Santos C. / III Interdisciplinary Conference on Biodiversity and Ecology

2016 Democratization of information in the context of territorial management Montevideo, Uruquav Gaucher L.\*, Hernández D., Grattarola F., Rodriguez-Tricot L., Duarte A., Perazza G. & González, S / III Interdisciplinary Conference on Biodiversity and Ecology

2016 Molecular detection of species and sex determination in road killed foxes in Uruguay Layras, Brazil Mannise N.\*, Cosse M., Grattarola F., Repetto L. & González S. / First Ibero-American Congress on Biodiversity and Road Infrastructure

## **SCI COMM**

2022 Scientific Pokemon Go

Podcast episode by Soledad Machado for Medios Públicos [episode]

2020 Biodiversidata began to digitize the herbarium of the National Museum of Natural History Press note by Leo Lagos for La Diaria [article]

2021 iNaturalist - What is it and what can it do for our project?

Talk with students of the Polo Educativo Tecnológico Arrayanes (Park Rangers) [slides]

#### 2020 Getting started with iNaturalist - Project RACATÚ

Online talk with primary school students from rural school N102 of Berachi (Cerro Largo, Uruguay) [slides]

#### 2020 Uruguayans are wanted to participate in a platform that helps scientists

Press note by Analía Filosi for Diario El País [article]

#### 2019 iNaturalist: a bet on citizen science

Talk at Museum of Natural History Torres de la Llosa [slides]

### 2019 iNaturalist a citizen science tool to improve biodiversity knowledge in Uruguay

Radio interview by Juan Vique in Radio Uruguay [radiocut]

#### 2019 The Uruguayan Consortium of Biodiversity Data, Biodiversidata, published the first open data set

Press note by Leo Lagos for La Diaria [article]

#### 2019 Series 'Gender and IT' - Pan Ceibal

Online talk with students from Canelones, Paysandú, Tacuarembó and Treinta y Tres' primary schools in Uruguay

### 2019 Biodiversidata: Biodiversity Open Data

Online talk at the Third Edition of 'Datos y Cogollos: Open Data in Uruguay'. La Diaria Media Lab (Montevideo, Uruguay)

### 2019 Exhibition 'A Computer of One's Own'

Art exhibition about pioneer women in Computer Science at CSSconf and JSConf (Berlin, Germany) [project]

#### 2018 Big data in biodiversity

Radio interview with Federico Weinstein in the science segment of the program Justicia Infinita, Radio Océano (93.9 FM) (Montevideo, Uruguay)

## 2017 The Marsh Seedeater

Video production for PROBIDES organization [video]

#### 2016 Drawn news: First record of a jaguarundi in Uruguay

Video production for JULANA NGO [video]

### REFERENCES

Petr Keil Czech University of Life Sciences, Czech Republic

keil@fzp.czu.cz | phone +420 776 371 840

Daniel Pincheira-Donoso Queen's University Belfast, UK

d.pincheira-donoso@qub.ac.uk | phone +44(0) 28 9097 2967

Lauren Weatherdon UN Environment Programme World Conservation Monitoring Centre, UK

lauren.weatherdon@unep-wcmc.org | phone +420 776 371 840

Susana González Clemente Estable Biological Research Institute, Uruguay

sugonza9@yahoo.com | phone +598 24861417